Guide to the Hatch River Expeditions video collection 1923-1998
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
Hatch River Expeditions video collection
1923-1998
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 (801) 581-8864
A0529
Hatch River Expeditions
49 VHS videocassettes, 2 8mm films, 2 Super 8mm films, 3 16mm films. 12 VHS are duplicates; three 16mm film reels are duplicates of VHS tape item 19.
The Hatch River Expeditions video collection (1923-1998) consists of movies documenting the Hatch family and Hatch River Expeditions river trips from the 1930s to the 1990s. Robert Rafael "Bus" Hatch and his family began guiding groups down the Green and Yampa Rivers in the mid 20th century, and their legacy is continued by the third generation Hatches still running their river running business.
Organizational History
Robert Rafael "Bus" Hatch and his brothers Alton and Tom began boating in the Vernal, Utah, area in the late 1920s. They ran the Green River in 1931, the Green and Colorado through Cataract Canyon in 1933, and the Grand Canyon in 1934. In 1935-36, they ran the Middle Fork of the Salmon River in Idaho, as well as the Main Salmon. By the end of World War II, Bus Hatch in particular had become known as a river runner. With the controversy over the planned Echo Park Dam in Dinosaur National Monument in the late 1940s and early 1950s, many people turned to Bus Hatch and his sons, Don, Ted, and Frank, to take them down the Green and Yampa Rivers. During the controversy, Hatch River Expeditions outfitted river trips for both pro-dam and anti-dam groups, trips that often included over 100 people. This was the true genesis of Hatch River Expedtions. After the controversy, and through the 1960s, the name Hatch became synonymous with river running, especially in the western United States. By the end of the 20th century, Hatch had become one of the best-known river outfitters in existence, and there are now 3rd generation members of the Hatch family who are still in the river running business.
The Hatch River Expeditions video collection (1923-1998) consists of films and videos that document Hatch river trips on the Green, Colorado, San Juan, Middle Fork of the Salmon, Selway, and other rivers, including some scenes of a 1956 river trip on the Indus River in Pakistan. The collection also contains films that document Hatch family history, including scenes in and around Vernal, Utah that depict family life, work, town scenes, hunting and fishing, skiing, and other family activities.
The collection is arranged in two parts: the 1987 donation, and the 2006 addendum. The 1987 addendum contains five films on two VHS videocassettes, of which one is not a Hatch family or Hatch River Expeditions trip. The 2006 addendum is arranged as follows: films; videocassettes, depicting Hatch family, including home movies and family river trips; river trips that were filmed by friends and passengers on Hatch River Expeditions trips, including promotional films and copies of videos made by passengers and later sent to Hatch River Expeditions; and non-Hatch videos, which are either videos obtained by Meg Hatch while she was on the Utah Travel Council Board, or were sent to Hatch River Expeditions or Hatch family members. All are arranged chronologically within these subdivisions.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
See also the Hatch River Expeditions photograph collection (P0781) and records (Accn 1325), the Charles Eggert photograph collection (P0766), audio-visual Collection (A0511) and records (Accn 1659), the Frederick Hoffman Wood photograph collection (P1037), and Dr. Robert Jerome Parsons photograph collection (P1236).
Hatch, Robert Rafael, 1902-1967; Rivers--West (U.S.); Rivers--Recreational use; Sports and Recreation; Moving Images; Moving images
- Hatch River Expeditions (1987 donation), 1923-1936; VHS videocassette (Cassette 1)
  Six films on one VHS videocassette:
  1. "Through the Grand Canyon of the Colorado River" Hatch-Swain-Frazier-Eddy trip through Grand Canyon, August 1934. 46:36
  2. Middle Fork of Salmon River trip, 1935 or 1936. 46:50 to 55:10
  3. Middle Fork of Salmon River trip, 1935 or 1936. 56:26 to 1:10:40
  4. Green River trip, 1932. Browns Park to Echo Park. 1:10:47 to 1:19:55
  5. "Sailing down the old Green River" 1932. Hideout Flat to Browns Park. 1:20:04 to 1:26:50
  [note: numbers 4 and 5 are part of the same film, but the order was reversed when they were transferred to the VHS tape]
  6. "The Survey of the Grand Canyon of the Colorado River in Arizona" Birdseye survey of the Grand Canyon by the U.S. Geological Survey, August-September 1923. This last film is not a Hatch river trip. 1:26:52 to 1:39:00
- >Hatch-Swain-Frazier-Eddy trip through Grand Canyon (1987 donation), 1934; VHS videocassette (Cassette 2)
  This item is a shorter, edited version of "Through the Grand Canyon of the Colorado River" from item 1. 33:19
- Hatch family home movies, 1930s-1950s; VHS videocassette (Cassette 3)
  Ted in boat at Green Lakes Lodge / Bus and Eva / Parade in Vernal? / Eva with other women, men, children, Royce (Cap) and Thelma Mowrey, / rodeo / man in suit / bird nest? / men by with with fish, Frank Swain, 10-man raft / flowers at funeral? / child with dog / family by river, deer in water, boat crossing river with horse swimming behind it in Island Park / wooden boats in rapids in Split Mountain / Royce (Cap) Mowrey, Eva, others [over-exposed], Bus, Hatch children (Don, Ted, Frank) swimming, women swimming (Eva?) at swimming hole / cock fight / kids skiing in Uintas? [9:30] / ski jumping at Ecker Hill / goose hunters / boy teasing rooster / people playing basketball / boy and girl on porch / building house, putting up forms / using horse-drawn scraper / waterfall in canyon / Canada goose, kids, geese along riverbank with Bus and family / Yampa River / wrecked boat / Nevills Expedition boats landing at Jensen, Utah [1940]/ towing Nevills Expedition boats with motorboat [1940] / Tetons, bear, Yellowstone National Park / rodeo in Vernal with trick riders, bronc riding, bull riding / fishing on upper Green, Bus with string of fish / powerboat / cock fight / horse, dogs / Bus and other man digging out coyote den / hunting camp with deer and men, camp scenes with Eva, tent blows down / building / lake in Uintas? / dog cart wrecks with child / fire tower / fish on string / dog with sleeping child / Don, Ted ice skating / cock fight / Gus in USMC uniform / Eva with flowers / house / boat on upper Green river / little boy using backhoe / family deer hunting / sledding / shooting .22 rifles / funeral with flowers / horse riding / cougar cubs, coyote cubs / children's parade in Vernal / lower Green River scenery / powerboat on river / wild horses / 7- and 10-man rafts in rapids/ mountain scenery / rodeo with bronc riding / rapids [older film] / horses running, walking / girls with dog / building / boy teasing dog with cat / camping, old truck / boats with Wes Eddington in his kayak [Desolation Canyon, 1940], wooden boats in rapids, Gunnison Butte, Tushar Dam, Green River [Utah] bridge / pontoon rafts in rapids / men scouting rapids in Cataract? / zoo with penguins, seals, elephants, bear, other zoo animals, redwood trees, beach, calm digging, flounders, zoo, bison, San Francisco, Bus in boat in San Francisco Bay, view of bridge from San Francisco Bay, ships, Catalina Island?, fishing, harbor, more fishing, boats, men, airplane taking off, aerial views of city and coast, men, party with mariachis, women, children, cathedral, fishing, gulls / Vernal scenes, 1950s / dog / men, girls, children.
- Hatch family home movies, 1930s-1950s; VHS videocassette (Cassette 4)
  1937 Yampa River trip with Eva, Roy and Madeline DeSpain, Wes Eddington and wife, Ruple Ranch, horses swimming across river in Island Park, Split Mountain / children swimming / ice breaking in river / capsize of pontoon raft in Indus River, Pakistan, 1956. 36:45
- "Don and Meg Hatch private trip", 1987; VHS videocassette (Cassette 5)
  River trip through Canyon of Lodore, Hatch family. Low water. At 28:30 changes to high water runs of Hells Half Mile rapid with Av Kay (family friend). Different trip. 40:45
- Don Hatch talk in Moab, Utah, 1989; VHS videocassette (Cassette 6)
  Don Hatch talking about river running history at unidentified event in Moab, Utah, 1987. 1:42:45
- "Av Kay Day", 1990 June 23; VHS videocassette (Cassette 7)
  One-day trip through Split Mountain Canyon that is a birthday surprise for Av Kay, family friend of the Hatch family. 41:00
- Don and Meg Hatch Christmas, 1993; VHS videocassette (Cassette 8)
  Stills of Hatch family members Don, Meg, John, Wendy, Clark, and other children and grandchildren. Made shortly before Don Hatch died. 10:00
- Charles Eggert films, 1951-1964; 1993; VHS videocassette (Cassette 9)
  Four films on one VHS videocassette:
  1. "This is Dinosaur" 1951. start to 26:29
  2. "Wilderness River Trail" 1952. 26:35 to 58:40
  3. "Boondoggle of a basin" 1952. 58:48 to 1:08:00
  4. "Sculptured Earth" 1964. 1:08:15 to 1:56:16
  First three films are about the Echo Park Dam controversy in the early 1950s. The US Bureau of Reclamation planned to build a dam on the Green River in Dinosaur National Monument, and the Sierra Club and other conservation organizations mobilized to fight it. Charles Eggert's films were instrumental in defeating the dam. "Boondoggle..." is about the Colorado River Storage Project in general, of which the Echo Park Dam was a part. It is Eggert's only attempt at animation. "Sculptured..." is a film that lays out the case for the creation of Canyonlands National Park in southern Utah. A screening of the film was banned from the University of Utah campus in 1964.
  Inserted in box is letter from Charles Eggert to Don Hatch, January 19, 1993, explaining how and why he made these video copies.
- Charles Eggert films, 1955-1956; VHS videocassette (Cassette 10)
  "A Canyon Voyage: the Eggert-Hatch Expedition, 1955-56. Video transfer from 16mm format version." Also includes "Danger River." These two films were made during the 1955-56 Eggert-Hatch expedition, the last river trip to follow the course of the Green and Colorado all the way from Wyoming to Lake Mead before Flaming Gorge and Glen Canyon Dams were begun in 1956. Film shows river from Green River, Wyoming, to Lake Mead, Arizona. 1:39:15.
- Charles Eggert films; Paul Winter film, 1955-1956; 1985; VHS videocassette (Cassette 11)
  Two films on one VHS videocassette:
  1. "A Canyon Voyage/Danger River" 1960s edited version with Charles Eggert's commentary on the making of the films and how they were re-cut and edited to use during the fight over dams in the Grand Canyon in the 1960s. 48:10
  2. "Canyon Consort" by Paul Winter. (c) 1985 48:10 to 1:45:49. This film may be protected by copyright.
- Hatch high-water Lodore trip, circa 1960; VHS videocassette (Cassette 11A)
  No date, no titles. Film shows a very high-water Hatch river trip through the Canyon of Lodore in the late 1950s or early 1960s. Film starts at Disaster Falls, shows runs of Triplet Falls and Hells Half Mile, and the approach to Echo Park, where it ends. 10:09
- "A River Odyssey", 1960s; VHS videocassette (Cassette 12)
  Narration/Script by John H. Chapman, photography/editing by George T. Henry. Five Seasons Productions, Cedar Rapids, Iowa. 1960s Hatch promotional film; notable for sideburns on crew, pliers on belts, cheesy 1960s music, building fires on the open ground, Mae West-style PFDs, surplus boats. One scene shows a Park Ranger in a decked canoe running a rapid; Glade Ross? Also shows Warm Springs Rapid on the Yampa River in its present state, so film must have been made after June 1966 when the rapid was formed. 35:00
- REI commercial, 1980s; VHS videocassette (Cassette 13)
  Commercial advertisement for opening of new Recreational Equipment Inc. store in unknown location, offering a Hatch River Expeditions trip as a door prize. Probably Salt Lake City store. 0:30 This film may be protected by copyright.
- Japanese-language travel film about Utah, 1987; VHS videocassette (Cassette 14-15)
  Japanese-language travel film about Utah tourism. Depicts two Japanese women traveling in Utah and going to popular tourist sites. Hatch River trip through Canyon of Lodore on Green River @ 50:30 to 58:48, with Don Hatch, Todd Gordon, Barry Hatch, and unidentified NPS employee. Segment on Utah Nippo newspaper @ 14:00 to 16:15] 1:08:00. This film may be protected by copyright.
- "Rivers of Time", 1991; VHS videocassette (Cassette 16)
  Clean, unedited copy of "Rivers of Time," a series produced by KUTV in Salt Lake City about the history of river travel on the Green River. Featuring Don Hatch, Clark Hatch, John Hatch, Roy Webb, and others. Note inserted in box from Larry Warren, producer and narrator, to Don Hatch saying "I thought you'd like a nice clean copy of the river series we did." cameraman: Scott Jones. 13:20. This film may be protected by copyright.
- "Undiscovered Dinosaur", 1991; VHS videocassette (Cassette 17)
  Series by KUTV about tourism in eastern Utah. Taped off nightly news broadcasts, contains much extraneous footage of news from 1991. Features Don Hatch, Dee Holladay, others. Canyon of Lodore segment @ 20:50 to 23:50; Yampa River @ 56:50 to 59:16; Yampa river again @ 1:13:45 to 1:16:37. 1:16:37. This film may be protected by copyright.
- "A Trip through Dinosaur National Monument", 1990s; VHS videocassette (Cassette 18)
  Hatch promotional film. Seven copies. 9:36
- "A trip through Dinosaur National Monument", 1980s; VHS videocassette (Cassette 19)
  Hatch promotional film. HIgh-water trip on the Yampa River, depicts scenery, petroglyphs, boats, camping, food preparation, other aspects of commercial river trip. Hairstyles,garish flowered Hatch hats, and design of Hatch logo on boats are diagnostic to the 1980s. Very little dialogue, mostly music. Seven copies. 9:36
- "Iowa Traveler" series raw footage, 1991 July 14-18; VHS videocassette (Cassette 20-21)
  KGAN-TV, Cedar Rapids, Iowa. Series "Iowa Traveler" depicts a river trip with George T. Henry of Cedar Rapids as the guide for Hatch River Expeditions. Raw footage taken on the trip includes scenes of loading boats, unloading boats, cooking, camping, interviews with participants, guides including George Henry and Mick Caldwell, Don Hatch, wildlife. 2:03:56 For more on George Henry from KGAN, see A0529 items 28-30. This film may be protected by copyright.
- "Iowa Traveler" series as broadcast, 1991 July 29-August 04; VHS videocassette (Cassette 22)
  "Iowa Traveler" series as broadcast on 29 July to 4 August 1991 on KGAN-TV, Cedar Rapids, Iowa. Documents Hatch River Expeditions trip with George T. Henry of Cedar Rapids as Hatch guide. Includes extraneous news footage. 53:25. For more on George Henry from KGAN, see items 28-30. This film may be protected by copyright.
- "Iowa Traveler" series Hatch promotional, 1991; VHS videocassette (Cassette 23)
  Footage taken from "Iowa Traveler" series on KGAN-TV, Cedar Rapids, Iowa, which depicts Hatch River Expeditions trip, 14-18 July 1991, and re-edited into a Hatch River Expeditions promotional video. 8 copies. 14:30.
- "Iowa Traveler" series Hatch promotional., 1991; VHS videocassette (Cassette 24)
- "Southwest Excursions", 1992; VHS videocassette (Cassette 25)
  By Wayne Schlipp. Subtitled "Cataract Canyon, Yampa and Green Rivers, and the rapids." Footage includes Cataract Canyon; Canyon of Lodore (with some footage from KGAN-TV series); and Monument Valley. 13:50
- "Yampa River & Ladore [sic] rafting trips, 1993; VHS videocassette (Cassette 26)
  By Wayne Schlipp. Proper spelling is "Lodore," but "Ladore" is a common error. 57:00
- Cataract Canyon, 1994 June; VHS videocassette (Cassette 27)
  Video of high-water Hatch River Expeditions trip through Cataract Canyon, June 1994. Features guides Dan Vernon and Mick Caldwell. Music only, no audio. 24:40
- "George's Last Ride" raw footage 1, 1995; VHS videocassette (Cassette 28-29)
  Raw footage from KGAN-TV series about the last trip taken by George T. Henry of Cedar Rapids, Iowa, as a Hatch River Expeditions guide. Contains some footage from 1991 series "Iowa Traveler." Includes interviews with Henry, Don Hatch, Meg Hatch, passengers, guides including Mick Caldwell, Mike Fahey, Justin Hoffman, camping scenes, cooking scenes, rapids. 1 of 2 tapes. 2:02:24. This film may be protected by copyright.. For more on George Henry from KGAN, see items 20-22.
- "George's Last Ride" as broadcast, 1995; VHS videocassette (Cassette 30)
  KGAN-TV series about the last trip taken by George T. Henry of Cedar Rapids, Iowa, as a Hatch River Expeditions guide, as broadcast. Contains some footage from 1991 series "Iowa Traveler." Includes interviews with Henry, Don Hatch, Meg Hatch, passengers, guides including Mick Caldwell, Mike Fahey, Justin Hoffman, camping scenes, cooking scenes, rapids. 27:40. This film may be protected by copyright. For more on George Henry from KGAN, see items 20-22.
- River trip, 1995; VHS videocassette (Cassette 31)
  Presented by Southwest Excursions, Wayne Schlipp. Special Thanks to: Hatch River Expeditions Cataract Canyon trip. Dan Vernon and Scotty, guides. Labyrinth Canyon scenes, hiking, camping, eating, music around the campfire, last night party. 54:00.
- Canyon of Lodore, 1996 July 12-14; VHS videocassette (Cassette 32)
  Features scenes of fire in Lodore, helicopters dipping water from river and dropping it on hot spots. No identification of guests or who made the tape. Ends at buffalo petroglyph in Island Park with "there goes the battery." 32:00
- "Three Great American Adventures", 1998; VHS videocassette (Cassette 33)
  Outside TV/Summit Films production. Film of kayaking trip in Glacier Bay, Alaska; rafting with Hatch River Expedtions on the Middle Fork of the Salmon River, Idaho; and climbing in the Grand Tetons. Hatch segment is 18:45 to 32:52. Guides Kevin Chanler, Roger Prais, Keirith Snyder. This film may be protected by copyright.
- Glen Canyon Dam flooding video, 1983; VHS videocassette (Cassette 34)
  "Challenge at Glen Canyon: Floodwaters of the Colorado River Basin-drainage and repair of the spillways at Glen Canyon Dam." Footage of 1983 flooding at Glen Canyon Dam, inspection and repair of spillways, release of water from spillways, etc. Also footage of 1983 floods in Salt Lake City, Utah. Not Hatch River Expeditions. 27:00
- "Impressions of Utah", 1987; VHS videocassette (Cassette 35)
  Utah Tavel Council. Four travel writers tour Utah and give impressions of the state. Dennis Hanson, Bend, Oregon; Bill Hughes, Los Angeles, California; Rick Sanders, Bedfordshire, England; Dewitt Jones, Bolinas, California. Sent to Meg Hatch when she was on the Utah Travel and Tourism Council. 1987. 23:00 Not Hatch River Expeditions. This film may be protected by copyright.
- "Utah Highlights", 1987?; VHS videocassette (Cassette 36)
  Utah Travel Council film about Salt Lake City. Sent to Meg Hatch when she was on the Utah Travel and Tourism Council. 16:30 Not Hatch River Expeditions. This film may be protected by copyright.
- "The Montana Centennial Wagon Train, 1889-1989", VHS videocassette (Cassette 37)
  Sent to Meg Hatch when she was on the Utah Travel and Tourism Council. 56:00 Not Hatch River Expeditions. This film may be protected by copyright.
- "River Time: Rafting the Middle Fork of the Salmon", circa 1990s; VHS videocassette (Cassette 38)
  Video about rafting trip on the Middle Fork of the Salmon River, Idaho. 38:33. Not a Hatch River Expeditions trip; marked "Review Copy" on tape. This film may be protected by copyright.
- "A River Odyssey", 1960s; 16mm film (Reel 39)
  Narration/Script by John H. Chapman, photography/editing by George T. Henry. Five Seasons Productions, Cedar Rapids, Iowa. 1960s Hatch promotional film; notable for sideburns on crew, pliers on belts, cheesy 1960s music, building fires on the open ground, Mae West-style PFDs, surplus boats. One scene shows a Park Ranger in a decked canoe running a rapid; Glade Ross? Also shows Warm Springs Rapid on the Yampa River in its present state, so film must have been made after June 1966 when the rapid was formed. 35:00 Three copies of film, one badly scratched.
- Home movies, circa 1950s; 8mm film (Reel 40)
  Film of hunting camp with Bus Hatch and family in the 1950s; airplane flight over Grand Canyon. 3:00. DVD copy available.
- Home movies, circa 1960s; 8mm film (Reel 41)
  View of salmon leaping up Dagger Falls, Middle Fork of Salmon River; Don Hatch's family? at overlook of Red Canyon, Green River; family getting into white 1950s Porsche 356 coupe; playing in lake at Green Lakes Lodge, Uinta Mountains. Box is labeled "mystery roll" 5:00. DVD copy available.
- Home movies, circa 1973; Super 8mm film (Reel 42)
  Don Hatch pumping up rafts and putting on life jackets on boats labeled "Canadian River Expeditions." Chilko River? malfunction in camera makes film jump. 3:00. DVD copy available.
- Home movies, circa 1973; Super 8mm film (Cassette 43)
  "Portage of boat" on Chilko River? in Canada, 1973? box is labeled "good roll" 3:00.
- Home movies, undated; Super 8mm film (Cassette 44)
  Underexposed, jumpy film reel; not able to see what it is about. Possibly Christmas morning? 3:00. DVD copy available.